<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of Mr. Benjamin Perkins, at the funeral of Mrs. Martha Robient, who deceased September the 15th, at Colchester, 1700 enlarged into a discourse on the excellent life and glorious death of a Christian, from 2 Tim. 4. 7,8 : with an enquiry into the reasons of the grand prohibition on the servants of God to continue here in his service, signify'd to them by death, from Heb. 7. 23 / by T. Beverley.</title>
            <author>Perkins, Benjamin.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1542aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43716</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475131</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151275</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90497)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151275)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2253:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of Mr. Benjamin Perkins, at the funeral of Mrs. Martha Robient, who deceased September the 15th, at Colchester, 1700 enlarged into a discourse on the excellent life and glorious death of a Christian, from 2 Tim. 4. 7,8 : with an enquiry into the reasons of the grand prohibition on the servants of God to continue here in his service, signify'd to them by death, from Heb. 7. 23 / by T. Beverley.</title>
                  <author>Perkins, Benjamin.</author>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Ptinted [sic] and are to be sold by John Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 44</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, faded, and tightly bound, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 2nd, IV, 7-8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews VII, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151275:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF Mr. <hi>Benjamin Perkins,</hi> At the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>Martha Robient,</hi> Who deceaſed <hi>September</hi> the 15th. at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> 1700.</p>
            <q>Enlarged into a Diſcourſe on the excellent Life and Glorious Death of a Chriſtian. <bibl>From 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>With an Enquiry into the Reaſons of the Grand Prohibition on the Servants of God to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue here in his Service; ſignify'd to them by Death: <bibl>From <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.23.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Marſhall,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151275:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151275:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151275:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151275:3"/>
            <head>TO Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> AND Mrs. <hi>Sarah Prior. Inhabiting the Town of</hi> Colcheſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My very Eſteemed Chriſtian Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I have taken the Full Freedom of changing, and making Additions to the Sermon committed to my Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal at your Deſire, and with the Conſent of Mr. <hi>Perkins;</hi> So I do in his Name, and I doubt not, with his Deſire, as well as my own, give it into your Hand, as Perſons ſo nearly concern'd in, and related to Her; who was the mournful, and alſo the to be rejoiced in, occaſion of it; as the Teſtimony of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Her, and of all the Kindneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from You, when with You in the occaſional Miniſtration of the Goſpel at <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi> As God hath made you, I am much perſwaded, Inſtruments of Good, where He hath placed You; ſo that He would bleſs You, and Your growing up Family, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie to You both, and make Conſolatory this Diſcourſe, and increaſe You in all Grace and Service to Him, is the Earneſt Prayer of; My Eſteemed Friends in the Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Faithful Friend, And Servant in Him,</hi> T. Beverley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:151275:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE Serious, Candid, Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>IT hath been always looked upon as one of the greateſt Points of the Wiſdom of a Man, to underſtand, and to conſider Death, to reſearch into all the Rules of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Conduct in the preparing for, and regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our Reception of it: All the great Men of Morals have Treated of it, as one of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Points of <hi>Morality;</hi> but it is the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Glory of the Word of God, to have underſtood the Way, and Path of this Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; before whom <hi>Death</hi> and the <hi>Grave</hi> are <hi>Naked</hi> and <hi>Open,</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> hath no <hi>Covering:</hi> That alone <hi>Teacheth to number</hi> our <hi>Days,</hi> ſo <hi>as to apply our Hearts</hi> to <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> To <hi>make wiſe,</hi> to <hi>underſtand this;</hi> to <hi>conſider our latter end:</hi> This gives the
<pb facs="tcp:151275:4"/>ſure Grounds of <hi>Hope</hi> in <hi>Death;</hi> yea, of Triumph, of appearing more than <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> over <hi>Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have conſidered the many Removes God hath of late made of many eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all Conditions; From that, ever to be with Honour remembred, <hi>Princeſs,</hi> the late <hi>Queen;</hi> that (ſo very lately) Illuſtrious young <hi>Duke of Gloceſter;</hi> that very Venerable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> A. B. C. thoſe truly Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Perſons, Judge <hi>Rokeby; Paul Foley,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> in his time Speaker of the <hi>Honourable Houſe of Commons:</hi> the very Eminent Chriſtian, the Lady <hi>King,</hi> late Wife to the ſo known Phyſician Sir <hi>Edmund King:</hi> Many Eminent Miniſters of the Goſpel, Mr. <hi>Thomas Cole,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Mather,</hi> Mr. <hi>Matthew Mead,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bates;</hi> with many others of very worthy Name; and I cannot omit, becauſe ſo early taken, that young Hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servant of Chriſt in the Goſpel, Mr. <hi>Philip King.</hi> The Conſideration of ſo many great Examples of Dying gave me deep <hi>Searchings of Heart,</hi> what the Reaſon and Meaning of ſuch Tranſpoſes ſhould be; and nothing hath given me greater Satisfaction, than the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections I have been enabled to make on the Great <hi>High Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> in whom the Charter of all the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God from the firſt Promiſe of him, <hi>Gen. 3.</hi> is founded, and whoſe Interceſſion Bears them up, and by whom they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved
<pb facs="tcp:151275:5"/>moved into Higher <hi>Galleries,</hi> Zach. <hi>3.</hi> into the <hi>Walks of Angels,</hi> who always ſtand by, or next the <hi>Preſence-Chamber</hi> of the <hi>Great King;</hi> waiting His Appearing and Coming forth in Glory; who hath the <hi>Unchangeable Prieſthood,</hi> Himſelf alone, <hi>made after the Power of an endleſs Life:</hi> In the mean time their Remove (as it appears) hath the more ſevere Style of a <hi>Prohibition,</hi> Heb. <hi>7.23.</hi> to expreſs it; or not being <hi>ſuffered to continue,</hi> by <hi>Reaſon of Death:</hi> This manner of ſpeaking, upon the Occaſion of the Death of that ſo Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable (beloved by all) Judge <hi>Rokeby</hi> made great Impreſſion upon me, and Thoughts of Heart; as in a Publick Congregation I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ſoon after; and it hath lain by me with an Intention of further Publication; For I know God is pleaſed with His ſurviving Servants, in rendring <hi>Precious the Death of his Servants</hi> gone out of this State; even as in his Sight, ſo in the Sight of others it ought to be precious, and not ſoon forgotten; and He is diſpleaſed, when the <hi>Righteous</hi> and <hi>Merciful</hi> are <hi>taken away,</hi> and <hi>none conſiders,</hi> nor <hi>lays it to Heart;</hi> when <hi>They are taken from the Evil to come,</hi> (Oh that now it may not be for that end) and <hi>each one reſts on his Bed, walking in their Uprightneſs,</hi> Eſay <hi>57.1.</hi> Such general Honourable Memorials are pleaſing to our never-dying <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> though the profuſe Praiſes of <hi>Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> no way encouraged hereby; the Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:151275:5"/>of the preſent Publication is, It having pleaſed God to remove a young Woman from a Family in <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> where I have had very kind Chriſtian Acquaintance and Reception; and had Opportunity of knowing and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that Perſon, as one, who gave all Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Hope of her Love to Jeſus Chriſt, his Truths, Holy Ways, and to his Servants, and of Faith and Hope in Him: A Sermon here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon was Preached in Remembrance of Her, by a Perſon, I muſt acknowledge a Stranger to me, my ſelf a Stranger to him any other way, than by Diſcourſe of Friends; this Sermon Preſented to Them by Him, was by Him and Them, my very eſtemeed Friends, the near Relations of the Deceaſed, put wholly under my Power; And that Grand Scripture, ſo every way Great in it ſelf, was ſo fitted to the great Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of a Diſcourſe on that <hi>Prohibition</hi> of the Servants of God continuing here; That, I hope, without any juſt Reaſon of Offence on either ſide, I took the Advantage of it, and not ſlighting, or waving, what I found to my Pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe in the Sermon, have yet taken the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to adapt all thereunto; and have with the moſt Chriſtian Friendly Reſpects to that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to that Family, and to the Memory of their deceaſed Relation; and as a Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of the before-recited, with all other, the Servants of God ſo lately remov'd, I have, as I Earneſtly Deſired to make it Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, ſo now done; And ſo, as that it may
<pb facs="tcp:151275:6"/>be both in Honour to them; and alſo may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to all the living Servants of Chriſt, as a Mirror of their own State in Life and Death; and that it might be bleſſed in general to all Readers; but above all, that it might be ſupremely to the Honour of the great Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that Happy Society of his Servants, who appoints each their Meaſure in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the Time of it, and lays his <hi>Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition</hi> upon them of exceeding either, by Death. To Him be the Glory, by the meaneſt and unworthieſt of his Servants, the Prayer of the Humbleſt Miniſter of his Goſpel,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Mon. 9. Day 10. 1700.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>T. Beverley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151275:6"/>
            <head>A FUNERAL SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2</hi> Tim. <hi>iv. Verſe vii. viii.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my courſe, I have kept the Faith: Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give me at that Day: And not to me only, but unto all them alſo that love his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>SOlomon</hi> the Wiſe tells us; <hi>To every thing there is a Seaſon, and a Time, a Time to be Born, and a Time to Die, a Time to Mourn, and a Time to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,</hi> Eccleſ. 3.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not, All the Godly and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and Senſible here preſent, will readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151275:7"/>acknowledge with me, That this is a <hi>Time to Mourn:</hi> But will it not look like the adventuring on a <hi>Paradox,</hi> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That it is alſo a <hi>Time to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Time</hi> it is indeed to <hi>Mourn</hi> for the loſs of ſo dear a Relatîon, and ſo Pious and Chriſtian a Friend: But are we not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as well as Men? And while Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture feeles, ſighs, nay ſinks at the diſmal Loſs of Friends, or Relations; Grace ſhould triumph over Nature, and Faith over Senſe. While we are bemoaning their loſs, we ſhould be Rejoycing in the Crown and Glory of Saints, of which number ſhe was we have ſo great Reaſon to be aſſured. Our Deceaſed Friend was one of their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who by their Holy Converſation give a plain, and ſenſible demonſtration of the Power of the Principles of our Holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, both by their Life, and their Death; For Words have not that <hi>Energy</hi> and <hi>Force,</hi> that Action and Converſation hath; a ſhining Life, and a triumphant Death, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade beyond all the Power of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or charms of Rethoric.</p>
            <p>And concerning the not only unblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, but Piouſneſs of her Life, for whoſe Death we now Mourn, it was ſo well known to all that knew her, that ſhe hath therein a better Character, than I can give her; for modeſty of Stile, and Reſerves of Expreſſion become me, when I conſider the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151275:7"/>Modeſty and Humility of her Deportment, through the whole of her Life.</p>
            <p>I come therefore now to the Text I have propoſed to Diſcourſe upon. The whole Text is drawn in Figures, borow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the <hi>Olimpic Games,</hi> well known in the Times, and Places in which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle wrote. <hi>Games</hi> appointed for all the activities of Perſons, prepared by Frame, and Conſtitution of Body, Vigour of Mind, and Inclination, and ſtrictly Diſciplined, Dieted, and Exerciſed thereunto: Such an alluſion is at other times made uſe of by the Apoſtle, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. And being Sanctified by the Divine Spirit, is moſt elegant and expreſſive of holy Senſes.</p>
            <p>In this Place <hi>The Apoſtle of the Gentiles</hi> gives us under theſe <hi>Emblems</hi> a threefold Character of himſelf; and then ſets out the Prize.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Encountring, and Combating all the Temptations of Satan within, and of the World without; wherein he <hi>Fought, not as one that beateth the Air,</hi> but at ſharps (as they ſay) with great effect for Offence and Defence, as thoſe Combatants alluded to uſed to do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He (who received the Prize) <hi>Finiſhed his Courſe.</hi> Therein he alludes to thoſe, who <hi>Run in a Race that they might Obtain: He Ran not as in certainly:</hi> He Ran the whole <hi>Courſe</hi> of Doing and Suffering, and of his Miniſtry, and Apoſtleſhip, the whole
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151275:8"/>
               <hi>Race ſet before him</hi> to the very <hi>Mark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He kept the Faith,</hi> the great Faith of the Goſpel, in union to the Crucified <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> which was the ſcandal of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> even the Croſs of Chriſt, and the <hi>Obedience</hi> of Faith in all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, <hi>Mortification</hi> to the <hi>World,</hi> and the Luſts of it within, and without; and doth extend to all kinds of Suffering, Heavenly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Mind, and Converſation: Hereby he behaved himſelf, as a mighty <hi>Champion,</hi> that by no means would let go his Hold, or <hi>Depoſium,</hi> the <hi>Pearl</hi> of <hi>great Prize,</hi> or ſurrender it to the violence againſt it.</p>
            <p>And ſo he leads us to the ſecond Part of this great Text, under the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, The <hi>Crown,</hi> or the <hi>Prize;</hi> not the <hi>Cornuptible Crown</hi> of thoſe Games, but the <hi>Incorruptible;</hi> to which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle refers, <hi>a Man is not Crowned</hi> except he <hi>ſtrive Lawfully;</hi> and herein he thus expreſſes himſelf; <hi>Henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Righteous Lord ſhall give me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I begin with the Firſt Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, I would conſider the Apoſtles Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of himſelf; <hi>I have Fought, I have Finiſhed, I have Kept.</hi> Now it is certain the Apoſtle, who acknowledges himſelf <hi>chief of Snners,</hi> and <hi>leaſt of Saints,</hi> would not ſpeak of himſelf, as in, or of, or by himſelf; but is to be interpreted by 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. &amp;c. <hi>By the Grace of God I am what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151275:8"/>I am; and not I, but the Grace of God that was with me.</hi> And <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.10. <hi>I Live, yet not I; but Chriſt Liveth in me.</hi> Altho' therefore at the firſt view, the Apoſtle may appear, as a ſelf-Subſiſting, a ſelf Confident Perſon in that three fold (I:) Yet when we duly weigh what he ſays in thoſe places, <hi>Not I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> It ſhews, when he ſpeaks thus, he conſiders himſelf as in Chriſt the <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Saviour of the Body,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented his, in all he Did and Suffered. But further, He is in all his united to him by Faith, He <hi>doth all their Works in them, and for them,</hi> and thus in him, by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they receive from him, by being <hi>ſtrong in the Grace, that is, in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> They do all, They do, ſo that the Apoſtle when he ſaith, (I) does not mean himſelf, by (I) as ſingle, ſolitary, divided from Chriſt; but as in him, by him; as to the Strength, Life, Principle he acted from. He did all in Chriſt; and not only ſo, but as the Power, and the Action flowing from it was in Chriſt; So the acceptance, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up the Imperfections, the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Guilt, the Corruption; <hi>The ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him free from the Law of Sin and Death;</hi> In regard of condemnation falling upon Sin <hi>dwelling</hi> in <hi>him.</hi> In all this, he looks wholly to Chriſt; and ſo his <hi>Figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Finiſhing his Courſe, keeping the Faith,</hi> Are to be limited; <hi>Not I,</hi> but Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone did all in me and was accepted for me in all.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151275:9"/>
            <p>This is therefore, the not only Encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement, but the very ſupport, nay more, the ſubſiſtnce of Saints in all their holy Action and Motion: All is in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And this is their conſolation in the midſt of ſo many Clouds of Guilt, and Imperfection; that they <hi>have a faithful and merciful high Prieſt who makes Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation;</hi> and perfumes their Perſons, and ſervices with his much <hi>Incenſe.</hi> And tho' many are ignorant of this great Goſpel Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, this was the conſolation of our Friend in her Dying Hours.</p>
            <p>Now this Explication of the Apoſtles as it ſhuts out on one ſide all the Phariſaic Boaſts in our ſelves, all the Self-righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Self-ſufficiency of Legaliſts; ſo it ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly condemns all the Licentious pretenſions of Carnaliſts, to live as they pleaſe; or to be Slothful, Negligent, Careleſs, Unactive in theſe great Tranſactions: For though they live all in Chriſt, depend wholly on Him for acceptance; yet all His are under the Holy <hi>Conſtraints</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> and the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of Filial Obedience; and Chriſt in them is a Principle of Spiritual Life, and Higheſt Activity. So that they can neither be looſe or plead <hi>Liberty</hi> as a <hi>Cloak of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,</hi> nor be dull, and ſtupid in the ways of Chriſt. And herein our Deceaſed Friend had learned Chriſt; In all things ſenſible of Duty; but Living as to Juſtification and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God above. With thoſe, who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151275:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the <hi>Circumciſion, Worſhipping God in the Spirit, rejoicing in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and having <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o confidence in the Fleſh,</hi> and ſo ſhe was able, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough ſo young a Perſon, to ſing the Song of Victory: <hi>O Death Where is thy Sting? )h Grave! Where is thy Victory? I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt my Lord, who hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iven me the Victory.</hi> This made Her ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtly deſire a remove out of the Body, <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have given the True Evangelical ſenſe of the Apoſtle placing ſo much upon himſelf, <hi>I have Fought,</hi> and <hi>Finiſhed,</hi> and <hi>Kept.</hi> 'Tis but as if he had ſaid, I have, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> can do all things through Chriſt ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing me:</hi> and I can look look upon all with Joy and Triumph, becauſe all my Impurities and Imperfections are anſwered for, and my Perſon is waſhed with the <hi>pure Water</hi> of his <hi>Sacrificing Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then conſider the great ſence of the Apoſtle; <hi>I have faught a good Fight.</hi> Wherein he comes forth in the ſtrength of <hi>Jehovah Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> As <hi>David the Warrior of the Lord,</hi> under the <hi>Captain of Salvation.</hi> Reſolved, and arm'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t all Points; and that had with Courage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Fidelity, almoſt now to the very laſt, carried on ſo far, as his Station reach'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he full Conqueſt and Victory of Jeſus Chriſt, he is now <hi>triumphing</hi> over all <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Explaining of this warfare, in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151275:10"/>the warrs of the Lord, as they are ſtil'd <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.14. We are to conſider the <hi>Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord mighty in Battle,</hi> who arms all his even the Lord Jeſus, who appoints them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who are therefore ſtiled <hi>Good Soldiers of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath Redeemed them from being ſlaves of Juſtice, of Wrath, of Satan; and they therefore are ſaid to <hi>over come by the Blood of the Lamb.</hi> So their very ſetting out is by his <hi>Blood;</hi> They are Arm'd by him with Courage, Spirit, and Might within. <hi>He teaches their hands to War, and their Fingers to Fight; by him they run through a Troop, by him they leape over a Wall;</hi> it is he that <hi>Girdeth them with ſtrength to the Battel, that they may help the Lord againſt the mighty;</hi> and that all Enemies may be ſubdued to him; and trherefore the Fight is called a good Fight with great Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtle had to Fight with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, his carnal Reaſon to <hi>Throw down the ſtrong holds of that, to bring every thought into Captivity to Chriſt,</hi> all thoſe high Thoughts of ſelf-Righteouſneſs, to ſlight all <hi>conferences with Fleſh and Blood, and to repel them, when tempted to ſuch dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal Treaties; to bring under the Law o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Members that warred againſt the Law of his Mind, and would bring him int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Captivity to the Law of Sin, and Death to bring under ſubjection that carnal Mind that is enmity to God; not ſubject to the Law
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151275:10"/>of God, nither indeed can be; that in dwelling Sin.</hi> All thoſe <hi>Willings</hi> and <hi>Luſtings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spirit;</hi> In regard of which, the Apoſtle Expreſſes himſelf in the Langu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of a Combatant in thoſe Games, that deals the moſt ſubduing, and mortifying Strokes and Blows; ſo he upon all Bodily Inclinations and Luſts. And this is one great Point of the good Fight, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle reviews with ſo much comfort: But it is in Chriſt, and through Chriſt, by whom, in whom as <hi>Crucified with him,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> with its <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> are <hi>Crucified</hi> and not in, or by himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle had to Fight with the World, in all both its inticements and bland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhments, and in regard of its Threats, Rages, and Perſecutions; In both regards ſaith He, <hi>I am Crucified to the World, and the World to me,</hi> Gal. 6.14. But it is in Chriſt, and his Croſs alone enabled Him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He had to Fight with all the Enemies of the Goſpel of Chriſt, in reſiſtance to the Grace of Chriſt in the Hearts of all, to whom He Preached; For ſpeaking of the Preaching of the Goſpel, He ſaith, <hi>The Weapons of our Warfare are mighty:</hi> So with the open profeſſed Oppoſitions to the Truth of Chriſt in his Redemption. To the <hi>Jews</hi> a <hi>Scandal;</hi> as it it was contrary to all the Revelation of God, in the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> and to the <hi>Gentiles Fooliſhneſs,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151275:11"/>as if it had no Agreement with the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Learning, and Wit of Men of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and Accompliſhment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He had to Fight with the <hi>Powers of Darkneſs, Spiritual Wickedneſſes in high Places;</hi> as every Chriſtian hath, For as He ſays, <hi>we War not;</hi> That is, not principally; <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Fleſh, and Blood, but againſt Principalities and Powers, the Rulers of the Darkneſs of this World.</hi> And for the maintaining this Fight, He had the ſame neceſſity with all Saints; <hi>To take to himſelf the whole Armor of God, that he might ſtand in the evil day, and having drne all to ſtand,</hi> Eph. 6.10.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All the Perſecutors, and their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, like the <hi>Beaſts of Epheſus,</hi> in what Senſe ſoever taken, He had to Fight with; wherein He ſuffered, <hi>as an evil doer;</hi> and was <hi>Killed all the Day long.</hi> But in all, <hi>He was more than a conqueror, through him who Loved him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. He had to Fight with Guilt, Death and the Grave, the <hi>Wrath to come;</hi> and with all the unbelief of his own Heart; But he <hi>over came</hi> by the continual Application He made to the Death and Reſurrection of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who <hi>Loved him, and gave himſelf for him, in whom he deſired to be Found.</hi> So that he Ran up to that aſſurance, to make that challenge, <hi>who ſhall lay any thing to my charge, as one of Gods Elect;</hi> to be aſſured, That neither <hi>Life, nor Death, Things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151275:11"/>nor Things to come, ſhould be able to ſeparate him from the Love of Chriſt;</hi> and ſo he could Sing that Triumphant Song; <hi>Oh Death where is thy Sting? Oh Grave where is thy Victory? The Sting of Death is Sin; the Strength of Sin is the Law, but thanks be to God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> as in the caſe of the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Death.</hi> All he places ſtill in Chriſt; and thus we ſee on all accounts, <hi>The Apoſtle Fought a good Fight,</hi> and through Chriſt had the Proſpect of a High and Noble End of the VVar, that is, of Victory.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>Head</hi> 2. I come then to the Second Point of the Apoſtles Triumphing Declaration of his own State in Chriſt; <hi>I have finiſhed my courſe;</hi> That we may rightly apprehend, Here are two things to be underſtood by it.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The General courſe of a Chriſtian State in its own Motion, Action, Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the Time of Converſion unto the very Hour of Death. This was one thing the Apoſtle underſtood by his courſe, for God having drawn out the Line of Life, as he hath ſeen fit for every one of his Servants; Their courſe of Chriſtian Action is by him drawn out proportionable; So that there is no part to be unadorn'd; Something of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, Private, Secret, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nholy Action is to be applyed to every part of it; There muſt be a <hi>Running</hi> to <hi>obtain:</hi> It is called therefore <hi>Running the Race, that is ſet before us; Looking to Jeſus;</hi> to ſhew in whoſe ſtrength
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151275:12"/>the whole Race is run; So, It is expreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>David,</hi> by his <hi>ſerving his Generation according to the will of God;</hi> and of <hi>Johns ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling his courſe,</hi> as a Servant of God in a Holy Converſation, beſides his Miniſterial ſervice: How many great concernments hath every Chriſtian to look to; His Implantation into Chriſt, Renovation, <hi>New Creation;</hi> The <hi>In-dwelling</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the Graces, and Fruits of it; His <hi>Living, walking in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; The work of Faith with Power; Sorrow after God working Repentance to Salvation never to be Repented of. The conſtraining Love of Chriſt, the living to him, the dying Dayly;</hi> Converſe with the <hi>Word of God, Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Reading, Meditation,</hi> Holy Diſcourſe, Prayer, Thankſgiving; Self-denyal, Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, being <hi>made meet to be Partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light:</hi> All theſe with much more ſet before us in Scripture, ſhew us, what the <hi>Race</hi> of a Chriſtan is; what his <hi>courſe</hi> is; Now to find our Heart engag'd herein, with all earneſtneſs <hi>Preſſing forward to reach the mark</hi> by the utmoſt ſtretch and extending our ſelves to it, is what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks of himſelf: He had run on in this Chriſtian courſe, on this Line, to very near the End of his Line of Life; and it is a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Review of a ſincere, much more of an Eminent Chriſtian; while he can behold Chriſt, the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Beginning, and End of All; All the Haltings, the Falls, Falſe-ſteps, the many Lingerings, made up,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151275:12"/>Anſwered, and Attoned for by the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and Finiſher of our Faith, who for the Joy ſett before Him,</hi> ran the whole courſe, the Father Lin'd out to Him, <hi>Doing always the things pleaſing in his ſight;</hi> Who ſet every ſtep according to his Obediential Love to the Father, and thefore went forth to his Death with higheſt Reſolution; <hi>Let us Ariſe</hi> (ſaith he) and (<hi>John</hi> 14.31.) <hi>Go hence: He endured the Croſs, deſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet down on the right hand of the Majeſty on High:</hi> And thus his ſervants <hi>follow his ſteps,</hi> and ſo we have reaſon to hope of this his Servant, that ſhe was ſwift, ſhe <hi>Finiſhed her courſe,</hi> ſhe Finiſhed the courſe ſhe was ſett in, though a more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and retired one, before ſhe was <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited,</hi> as the true ſenſe of that word, we Tranſlate <hi>(Not ſuffered)</hi> ſignifies, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.21. <hi>To continue any longer therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is yet a higher, and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted ſenſe of the Apoſtle <hi>Finiſhing his courſe;</hi> not a more ſubſtantial or Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental ſenſe; For that is indeed the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental; All the redeemed of Chriſt in, and by him, running their courſe, and ſo entring into their <hi>Maſters Joy;</hi> but there was alſo in all times a more Publick, and high ſphere of Action; Into which God hath been pleaſed to raiſe ſome of his ſervants; and there hath not been a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, then the Miniſtry of the Goſpel and moſt particularly, the Apoſtolick; and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151275:13"/>this undoubtedly the Apoſtle had regard, when he here ſaith, <hi>I have Finiſhed my courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For herein the Apoſtle had a Line given to him and a <hi>meaſure,</hi> the <hi>meaſure of the Line,</hi> which he would not <hi>ſtretch himſelf, nor into other Mens Labours,</hi> but according the Rule or Line preſcribed him by God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this was ſo abundant, that he <hi>Laboured more abundantly,</hi> then <hi>any other,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.10. <hi>He was the Apoſtle of the Gentiles, Miniſtring the Goſpel of God</hi> ſo to them, that the <hi>offering up of the Gentiles</hi> might be a <hi>Sacrifice, Acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> being <hi>ſanctified by the Holy Spirit;</hi> which was indeed a high ſphere of Chriſtian Goſpel-Activity; and whereof he ſaith, <hi>He might Glory;</hi> And <hi>the Line was ſo every way enlarged,</hi> that he <hi>Preached</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> round <hi>about from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem to Wyricum,</hi> Rom. 15.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He did fully, or <hi>Fulfil to Preach the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>He ſtrived to Preach where Chriſt had not been Named;</hi> And all this was made efficacious, by <hi>Mighty Signs,</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> by the <hi>Power of the Spirit of God.</hi> So that it was beſt for the Churches, and more needful he ſhould <hi>continue, though to his loſs,</hi> Phil. 1.21. In all this Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; He was moſt mindful to aſcribe all to <hi>Grace,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.10. <hi>By the Grace of God he was All,</hi> that <hi>He was;</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151275:13"/>and after all his Diſcourſe of <hi>his Line,</hi> and <hi>meaſure,</hi> He concludes; <hi>He that Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Let him Glory in the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.17. The Apoſtle <hi>Finiſhed this courſe,</hi> under and by the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of <hi>our Profeſſion,</hi> whoſe the fupreme Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in all is; Inaſmuch as <hi>He,</hi> who <hi>Built the Houſe hath more Honour,</hi> then the <hi>Houſe;</hi> whoſe <hi>Houſe</hi> with all <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> Heb. 3.1. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was; For He, who <hi>Built All Things</hi> in his Church, is <hi>God</hi> and <hi>our Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Head</hi> 3. I come now to the third Head, or Character, the Apoſtle gives of himſelf. <hi>I have kept the Faith:</hi> This Completes the whole: Herein the Apoſtle ſpeaks again, as a mighty Champion, that retain'd the Riches of Faith, <hi>Much more precious, then of</hi> Gold, <hi>that Periſheth:</hi> The Faith he retain'd with ſuch a Might, and would by no means ſuffer it to be forced out of his Hand.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Great Principal, and moſt eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Faith, the Apoſtle kept, or held faſt, is Jeſus Chriſt Himſelf, and his Righteouſneſs, who is pleaſed, becauſe he himſelf is indeed the All of Faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be ſtyled <hi>Faith</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is the whole Truth of the Goſpel, as the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> gives it the Honourable Title of the <hi>Faith once, at once,</hi> once for All; <hi>Delivered to the Saints,</hi> Jude 3. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151275:14"/>the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Faith</hi> by which the <hi>Juſt Live,</hi> and receive even full aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of underſtanding: <hi>The Righteouſneſs of God revealed from Faith to Faith;</hi> The <hi>Faith</hi> embracing the <hi>truth that is after Godlineſs,</hi> which whoever walks contrary to, <hi>denies the Faith;</hi> The Faith that looks to the Eternal State and Condition; which <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> denying by ſaying, <hi>The Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was paſt already, overthrew the Faith of ſome.</hi> This the Apoſtle held faſt in all the ſenſes of it, now given, and would by no means part with, or betray to any Seducers, or Adverſaries of one ſort, or other; as was before aſſerted under the firſt Character of <hi>Fighting a good Fight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The inward Grace of Faith in the Heart, and Holy confeſſion of which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>With the Heart, Man believes unto Righteouſneſs, and with the Mouth confeſſion is made to ſalvation; The Life, he liv'd by the Faith of the Son of God,</hi> who loved him and gave himſelf for him. The Faith even the <hi>Plerophory</hi> of it, <hi>ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Heart from an Evil Conſcience by the Blood of Jeſus,</hi> the Faith, by which we <hi>have Peace with God,</hi> the faith that <hi>embraces the Promiſes,</hi> by which we <hi>cleanſe our ſelves from all Filthineſs of Fleſh, and Spirit; the ſheild of faith,</hi> The Apoſtle Exhorts <hi>above all to take, to quench the fiery Darts of the Devil;</hi> The faith, by which the <hi>Elders ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſo Honourable a Teſtimony, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151275:14"/>Heb. 11. In all thoſe their great Acts; The faith that paſſes through all afflictions, temptations, and tryals, till thoſe Pillars are ſet up with this Inſcription, Rev. 13. <hi>Here is the Faith and Patience of the Saints, here are they, who</hi> keep the Commandments of God, and <hi>hold the Teſtimony of Jeſus;</hi> Laſtly the faith, the very preſence of <hi>things hoped for,</hi> raiſes to that <hi>Plerophory</hi> of <hi>hope, that enters within the Veil.</hi> All Saints with the Apoſtle who by faith have <hi>dyed,</hi> and <hi>ſlept in,</hi> and by <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and are <hi>entred</hi> into reſt with him, even as this ſervant of the Lord hath lone by the ſame faith; and whom <hi>God even our Lord Jeſus</hi> will <hi>bring with</hi> him, the <hi>Living remaining</hi> Saints ſhall not <hi>Anticipate; The Lord my God will come, and all his Saints with him:</hi> But in all this faith, our whole ſubſiſtence is in, and by the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> and <hi>Finiſher of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo we are come to the ſecond part of the Text; <hi>Henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> This is the <hi>Prize of the High Calling of God in Jeſus Chriſt; Eternal Glory, the Eternal Inheritance, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Redemption;</hi> the whole Excellency, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Bleſſedneſs of the Eternal State is <hi>the Inheritance of the Saints in Light;</hi> which is alone by Jeſus Chriſt in us, the <hi>Hope of Glory reſerved in Heaven:</hi> This the <hi>Lord</hi> as a <hi>Righteous Judge gives,</hi> and he gives as a <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> Becauſe Jeſus Chriſt hath purchaſed it with his own
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151275:15"/>Blood, and Obedience; And in him, it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Saints are able to ſubſiſt in this Eterna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Glory; Being <hi>made like him,</hi> by <hi>ſeeing hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as he is;</hi> but moſt <hi>Glorious,</hi> herein is tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> State, <hi>He in the Father, the Father in Him</hi> and Saints hereby in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and in <hi>the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and <hi>the Love</hi> wherewith the Fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Loved Him, even <hi>before the Foundation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the World</hi> is in them, becauſe <hi>He is in them</hi> and in all this the Son Intercedes with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Father,</hi> as a <hi>Righteous Father,</hi> John 17.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To open this part of the Text, accordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Tenor of the preſent Diſcourſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> far, as we have proceeded.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That expreſſion of the Apoſtle; <hi>Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> forth,</hi> or as the word in the <hi>Greek</hi> ſignifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That which remaineth is, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> laid up for me,</hi> &amp;c. An expreſſion ſuitab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to this is that, Heb. 4.9. <hi>There remaineth reſt for the People of God;</hi> This hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Immutable certainty; If the Judgment wicked Men be <hi>laid up in ſtore</hi> with Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Sealed among his treaſures,</hi> Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 34. How much more the Salvation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Glory, and Bleſſedneſs of his Saints: It as cerrain, and much more certain, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in themſelves, the precedent <hi>Fighting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good Fight,</hi> &amp;c. For their aſſurance is not themſelves; They would fail and come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hind, as Combatants not <hi>obtaining the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> If all the certainty were in themſelves; the <hi>Angels</hi> not <hi>Elect,</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> fail'd, or f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:151275:15"/>ſhort: But the Prize it ſelf to be given to them, who do <hi>Fight,</hi> and <hi>Run,</hi> is in the nature of the thing out of themſelves, and in God alone; and is aſſur'd by his Righteouſneſs, and Veracity, that cannot fail. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder is ſo Connexed, as not poſſible to be ſeparated, from what went before; and more Impoſſible by far to fail, then what went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as in us, but as all is ſure in the Great <hi>ſurety,</hi> It is to be fulfilled in all his; Even as the Debt He paid for them is ſet far above all doubts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In this aſſurance of the <hi>Prize,</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaks ſo triumphingly of, he ſays, <hi>The Lord, the Righteous Judge ſhall give me;</hi> He Styles the Lord, <hi>the Judge,</hi> and <hi>the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge,</hi> in agreement with the cuſtom of thoſe Games; In which there was a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſolemnly conſtituted, who ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge the Prizes, and Determine the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the ſtriving,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, a Man is not Crowned, <hi>except he ſtrive Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</hi> And it was expected from ſuch a Perſon in that State of Honour, that he ſhould be Fair, Equal, and Juſt in all his Judgment, and Determination; and it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures the Judgment of the Lord to be in all things, admirable for its greateſt Equity, Righteouſneſs, and Judgment; <hi>For the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eous Lord Loveth Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pſal. 11.7. And thus in alluſion to this in that ſo known Seat of alluſion to theſe <hi>Games,</hi> the Apoſtle ſays; <hi>I keep under my Body,</hi> and with the Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151275:16"/>methods, <hi>Bring it into ſubjection;</hi> Leaſt while I Preach to others; I my ſelf ſhould become one <hi>Rejected,</hi> to whom the Prize is not Judg'd; one unworthy the Prize; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he who Determines, is a <hi>Righteous Judge,</hi> and will not be Impoſed upon with outſides, or Formalities.</p>
            <p>But here the great doubt is, where is the Saint to be found, who can ſtand before a Judge, <hi>a Righteous Judge, ſuch a Righteous Judge as the Lord is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the alone Anſwer is, according to what hath been ſaid already; That it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends wholly upon what hath been done by the <hi>Captain of their ſalvation;</hi> His Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and his Sacrifice, the <hi>Author,</hi> and <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of Faith;</hi> What he hath done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them; That, in which he was wholly alone, and none of his with him; and that which he works in all his, as their <hi>Head</hi> of Life, and Influences; making them ſtrong in the <hi>Grace,</hi> that <hi>Reſides</hi> ſupremely, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally in <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and flows continually into them; and that by way of inward Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Poſſeſſion, by his <hi>Dwelling in them,</hi> John 6.57. And they in him; <hi>Even as the Living Father ſent him, and he Lives by the Father, ſo all Believers live by Him and in Him;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then being the Fundamental Merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Account; <hi>Chriſt All,</hi> and <hi>in All,</hi> there is a Glorious, Reſplendent Juſtice, and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Gods Adjudication of the Prize to all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151275:16"/>Saints in Him; Becauſe there is an exact Ballance, between what is Chriſts, and the Glory of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and of the <hi>Prize;</hi> So that Scripture delights in the uſe of the Word, <hi>Juſt, Righteous, Righteouſneſs</hi> in the Admenſuration to all in Chriſt <hi>at that Day Juſt,</hi> and the <hi>Juſtifier of Him that believes in Jeſus;</hi> He is <hi>Juſt to forgive us our Sins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſueſs,</hi> by way of Acquitance, and Judiciary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge; becauſe, <hi>The Blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son</hi> hath by <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and Sacrifice for ſin, firſt cleanſed <hi>from all unrighteouſneſs,</hi> 1 John 1.10. And there is an Illuſtrious <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> in the <hi>Judgment of God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; And a Flag of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyance againſt all Adverſaries, the Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Malicious Devils, and enraged Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wicked Men, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hung out; <hi>(we tranſlate a manifeſt token) in that Day,</hi> a Day of <hi>Adjudging</hi> the Prizes; That Day of the <hi>Revelation of the Righteous Judgment of God,</hi> Rom. 2.5.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Crown is call'd, as in ſome places a <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.4. And a <hi>Crown of Life;</hi> So here a <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs,</hi> as due to Chriſt in his; though to us, as in our ſelves, It is a <hi>Crown given,</hi> the <hi>Gift of Free Grace;</hi> as <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to <hi>Death the wages,</hi> due demerit, or deſert of Sin: It is <hi>Free Gift</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt, upholding the Glory of Juſtice, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in that Gift.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151275:17"/>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Crown</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) ſhall be given at that Day; There are two Times eminently Styled in Scripture, <hi>that Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Day of the firſt opening of the Glory of the Goſpel; and after a time of Eclipſe by the <hi>Anti-chriſtian Apoſtacy,</hi> ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out again in Glory; In which firſt and laſt the great <hi>Prophecies</hi> of Scripture are <hi>Fulfilled;</hi> we find therefore often in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; In thoſe Days,</hi> and <hi>In that Day,</hi> as all Compriz'd under that great Point of time, the <hi>Fulneſs of time; the appearance of Chriſt in the Fleſh,</hi> Gal. 4.4. And the time from thence running to his appearance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The, <hi>that Day</hi> of the <hi>Appearance</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and of his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> as they are joyn'd a little before the Text; that <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of All I imas,</hi> when all ſhall be placed, that is Happy and Bleſſed under their <hi>Head,</hi> Eph. 1.10. And ſo <hi>that Day</hi> is often uſed in the Epiſtles of the <hi>Now Teſtament;</hi> as here, and continually; that <hi>Great Day,</hi> that <hi>Day,</hi> wherein ſhall be ſo Glorious an Unveiling, a <hi>Revelation</hi> of the things, that have now been kept ſecret, but ſhall then be ſett out in the trueſt, and moſt Glorious Light; The Beauty of every thing in its own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeaſon, to which God hath referr'd in that General Table of time, God hath drawn, and that <hi>Solomon</hi> gives in ſhort the Heads off, in that ſo wiſe Book, the Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> or of <hi>the Preacher.</hi> At the End of the ſeveral events, there recorded;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151275:17"/>ſaying, <hi>God hath made every thing Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in its ſeaſon;</hi> But, becauſe it does not, or may not without wiſe References to that Eternal World be underſtood to be ſo; He ſays, God hath ſett Eternity, or the Eternal World in their Hearts, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then alſo are all the Great <hi>Miſteries</hi> of the Goſpel ſhall be clearly unfolded, and laid open; All the various dealings of God with his own, and with the Men of his preſent <hi>Hand,</hi> and might; the Men of <hi>this World;</hi> ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddled, and diſengaged from all their Darks, and Intricacies, and the <hi>Crown</hi> ſett with <hi>Glory,</hi> and the <hi>Glory of Righteouſneſs</hi> on all his Saints: And this becauſe it is the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of the <hi>Righteous Judgment of God;</hi> And then as the wicked ſhall be all in Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, <hi>Tribulation, Anguiſh,</hi> and Amazement; So Chriſt will be <hi>Glorified</hi> in the <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Admired,</hi> in all them, who <hi>believe,</hi> who have <hi>Fought the Good Fight,</hi> ſo as <hi>not to beat the Air; They have run</hi> not as <hi>Incertainly,</hi> and as in Naval Conteſts, have not <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack'd,</hi> but held faſt the <hi>Faith:</hi> And ſo the <hi>Crown</hi> Adjudg'd to them by the <hi>Righteous Judge</hi> of the Combatants, and their Activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in and through their great <hi>Agonothetes,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt and the ſupreme <hi>Agoniſtes,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of All, and cheif Combatant.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Apoſtle joyns with himſelf all thoſe, who, <hi>Love the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as thoſe, whom the <hi>Righteous Judge</hi> will <hi>give the Crown of Righteouſneſs unto,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151275:18"/>And this expreſſion offers two conſiderations to us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſeeing, the Apoſtle gives this ſhort Character of Saints in General, and not ſo particularly, (as <hi>Fighting</hi> the <hi>good Fight; Finiſhing all their courſe,</hi> and <hi>keeping the Faith,</hi>) but <hi>Loving the appearance of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt;</hi> It ſhews, there may be; and there is a different eminency of Saints; But as they all meet in the <hi>Head, Root, Corner Stone;</hi> So whatever their different meaſures are in making up the <hi>full ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in Chriſt,</hi> yet they are all alike in the <hi>Glory,</hi> the <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is all given by grace in Chriſt, and ſo the Leaſt, as well as the greateſt are <hi>Crown'd</hi> in Him; He gives the ſame <hi>Crown</hi> to the Laſt, as to the Firſt, even as in the <hi>Parable,</hi> Mat. 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that all Saints Love the <hi>Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Chriſt,</hi> it is made certain; They are thoſe, that have <hi>Fought, Run,</hi> held faſt the great <hi>Depoſitum, Committed to them,</hi> ſo as to obtain, and not to be rejected; the <hi>Faith,</hi> which gives them the aſſurance, and lifting up of the Head at the appearance of the great <hi>Judge,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrator</hi> of the <hi>Prize;</hi> and ſo they deſire, long for, and <hi>Love his Appearance;</hi> And thus I have given a breif View, and Examination of the words of this Great Text.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151275:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> That which I would now infer from the whole diſcourſe by way of Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal concluſion, by way of Practical enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by way of Conſolation, relating to the particular occaſion, ſhall be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That we would look to it; To <hi>hold the Faith</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt in its own <hi>Purity;</hi> For the Goſpel is ſo pure, ſeparate from all mixtures, as <hi>Silver Purified in a Furnace of Earth, Purified ſeven Times,</hi> that we muſt not <hi>pervert it</hi> any way; <hi>Every Word of God, Prov.</hi> 30.5, 6. Much more the Great Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Points: Whoever add to it, or diminiſh from it, will be <hi>found Lyars unto it;</hi> Bleſſed are they that <hi>truſt in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> It will be to them a <hi>Sheild of Salvation.</hi> As to that Great Point, <hi>Righteouſneſs by Faith</hi> in Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>works;</hi> How ſuddenly do Men ſlide down to <hi>Another Goſpel</hi> under the Apoſtles <hi>Anathema;</hi> and yet <hi>It is not another,</hi> but the clear, pure ſtreams of Goſpel-Truth and Grace are hereby troubled; and the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and comfort of Believers diſturb'd, and the Invitingneſs of it to ſtrangers much obſcur'd and defiled: Now here in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility of the Enemies of the pure Doctrine of the Goſpel is ſeen; That they being afraid to take up the Inſolent, Anti-chriſtian Word; <hi>Merit,</hi> or as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Debt.</hi> They would yet Privily bring in ſuch a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed preſence of works after Grace, as <hi>ſincere obedience,</hi> though not <hi>perfect</hi> into Juſtification, as the condition of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151275:19"/>upon which it juſtifies; even as perfect obedience was the condition of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works;</hi> and yet merit not once Named nor Allowed; Becauſe <hi>Adams</hi> ſtrength to work by, if he had rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed it, was indeed from the Bounty and Goodneſs of the Creator; yet as in a way of Condecency, of ſuch a Creator to ſuch a Creation, as the <hi>Humane Nature;</hi> that came pure and perfect out of His Hand: But what Believers do is from Grace in Chriſt, by and from <hi>His Spirit,</hi> Vouchſafed to Sinners, and ſo cannot <hi>Merit:</hi> Now this hath indeed very great Truth in it; Yet it doth not Anſwer the High Expreſſion of the Goſpel, excluding all Created, or Creature Righteouſneſs in the Court of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Juſtification; and placing all in the Righteouſneſs of God by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt; In his obedience, in his Expiation, Filling up, and ſo repleniſhing that Court; That nothing elſe can enter, but is kept out by the <hi>Flaming Sword</hi> of the <hi>Fiery Law:</hi> Yea, Angels that never ſinn'd, yet <hi>Cover their Faces,</hi> Eſa. 6. and their <hi>Feet,</hi> their Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and the <hi>Nakedneſs,</hi> and <hi>Folly</hi> of all Created Being before Increated and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt</hi> in and by Chriſt: Chriſt, as the Head of Amity, and Perſeverance in their Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous State, and <hi>Adam,</hi> not Flying to it upon thoſe tenders of it ſignifid to Him, as by that real evidence of it; That he was, and could be no more, then the <hi>Figure</hi> of Him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151275:19"/>
               <hi>that was to come,</hi> Rom. 5.12. And that His, and His Poſteritys ſtanding in Him, was only their ſtanding in Chriſt; as this was alſo repreſented in thoſe <hi>Sacramental Types, the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil,</hi> Gen. 2. Warning Him againſt ſubſiſting in Himſelf, as a <hi>God knowing,</hi> or able to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> but to look to the <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> ſo great a <hi>Type</hi> of Chriſt; as we find in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> Nothing therefore can enter into the Court of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> but Poor empty ſingle Faith Receiving, Owning, Acknowledging, <hi>Grace; Receiving Grace in Abundance,</hi> (excluding all elſe,) and the Gift of Righteouſneſs by Jeſus Chriſt alone; And to this it is enabled by Grace, and Accepted only for that Righteouſneſs ſake it does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
            <p>As to the enforcement by way of Action, and Practice, we ſee in this Great Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, the Apoſtle gives of a Man in Chriſt; that <hi>Fights the Good Fight, Finiſhes his Courſe, keeps the Faith;</hi> That a Believer in Chriſt is not a Looſe, or an Idle, Slothful, Unactive Perſon; but ſhall appear in <hi>that Day,</hi> as of the <hi>Overcomers</hi> in thoſe ſo Famed Games, or Exerciſes of all Proweſs, Courage, Action; ſo as to be judg'd worthy of <hi>thoſe Crowns</hi> of which they were ſo Ambitious, though but corruptible, by the juſteſt Judges, or Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of them; So the Saints ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented before the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Eternal Spirit of Holineſs</hi> and before <hi>Saints,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151275:20"/>and <hi>Angels,</hi> to the Terror, and Amazement of all the Loſt, as Perſons of diſtinct Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; and the <hi>Overcomers,</hi> as in the <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyptic</hi> Expreſſion is repeated; and yet all in Chriſt, and to the <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Praiſe of Grace</hi> in Him; So that the Doctrine of Free Grace is indeed the moſt Powerful, Effective, Fruitful Doctrine of Holyneſs, and ſo is moſt Diſcriminative of Perſons in Chriſt, and with greateſt ſeverity on thoſe, who are not; and of thoſe, who ſhall be thought worthy of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and who not; and yet without the leaſt Injury to <hi>Free Grace</hi> in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Great Conſolation have they, who knew our Deceaſed Friend; who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Admiring, Adoring thoughts of <hi>Free Grace;</hi> and thereby a great ſenſe of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Holineſs in the Fear of God,</hi> but all through <hi>Chriſt ſtrengthning</hi> Her; and in <hi>Fighting, Running, holding faſt,</hi> an Eye to the Crown, but as purchaſed for her by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; and that therefore ſhe <hi>Loved the Appearance of Jeſus;</hi> When the Crown al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready received, ſhall with Glory be ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her at <hi>that Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we may yet enter into the deeper enquiry into, and conſideration of all this Triumphant Declaration of the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Himſelf, and all Saints in that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Point; their receiving the <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> I will propoſe to give a breif reſolution of theſe following Points.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151275:20"/>
            <p n="1">1. How in the loſt undone State of the Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> there can ariſe ſuch a Generation of Servants of God, both more eminent and ſmaller in this World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How, or why they fall all under the <hi>Prohibition</hi> of <hi>ſerving God</hi> any longer here in the World, then the <hi>Finiſhing</hi> ſuch a <hi>Courſe</hi> of ſervice on ſuch a <hi>Meaſure</hi> of their <hi>Line</hi> Preſcribed by God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why this <hi>Prohibition</hi> is ſerv'd upon them by <hi>Death;</hi> Two Perſons only, <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> and why they only excepted.</p>
            <p>Herein I ſhall with all the care and Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to the underſtanding given to me by, and from the Word of God Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe each of theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Point.</hi> 1. It is indeed the wonder of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace, and Power; That there ſhould have been, and are ſuch a Generation of the Servants of God in the World, in every Age down to the preſent Time, in the midſt of ſuch a World of Men, Ignorant of God, <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enated from his Life, without God in the World, without Chriſt and Enemies in their Minds;</hi> ſo much given up to the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Luſts</hi> of it, as to be called; <hi>The World</hi> and the <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>this World,</hi> in a State of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to God, and his Kingdom; the <hi>Seed of the Serpent, the Dragon,</hi> Haters of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and on all opportunities <hi>Slaying them;</hi> as <hi>Cair,</hi> the <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Wicked one,</hi> Did <hi>Abel</hi> in the very Beginning; That yet in the midſt of all theſe, there ſhould be a Generation of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151275:21"/>Men and Women, that ſhould be in an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a courſe, a Lincal ſucceſſion of the Saints and Servants of God, like the ſucceſſion, as in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Levi,</hi> of the <hi>Preiſthood;</hi> and of the <hi>High Preiſthood</hi> in the Family of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron;</hi> the more Eminent, and the leſs Eminent among the Servants of God; but all a <hi>Royal Prieſthood;</hi> or like the Stars of the <hi>Firſt Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude</hi> in the Regions above, and thoſe they call, the <hi>Sporades,</hi> the Multitude of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Stars.</p>
            <p>Now the very Root, and Foundation and Corner Stone of all this is; That Grand <hi>Elect Servant</hi> of God, in whom <hi>His Soul delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> who in Raiſing up a Generation of the Servants of God, dealeth with all mildneſs; <hi>A Bruiſed Reed ſhall He not break, nor ſmok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Flax ſhall He quench,</hi> but ſhall <hi>ſend forth Judgment unto Truth of Victory,</hi> Eſa. 42.1. That <hi>Servant</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> with the <hi>Key of David on his ſhoulder,</hi> and ſtrengthn'd with the <hi>Girdle</hi> of <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> The <hi>Nail faſten'd in a ſure place,</hi> Eſa. 22.20, &amp;c. Upon whom is <hi>Hung all the Glory of his Fathers Houſe, the off-ſpring,</hi> and the <hi>Iſſue; All Veſſels</hi> of <hi>Greater</hi> and <hi>ſmaller Quantity,</hi> from the <hi>Veſſels of Cups, even to All the Veſſels of Flagons;</hi> Had not He been a Servant in the Foundation, There had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been a <hi>Servant of God in the World.</hi> It is He, who hath <hi>Loved,</hi> and <hi>waſhed in His Blood;</hi> and conſtituted <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Preiſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God</hi> and <hi>His Father,</hi> Rev. 1.5.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151275:21"/>
            <p>Now the Charter of His making Servants to God among the Children of Men, was given to the <hi>Second Adam:</hi> Immediately up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Fall of the Firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo quick and immediate as to ſurprize the Power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than in the Firſt Effort; when God in a Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clary proceſs upon Sathan, ſays, to Him, under the diſguiſe of the <hi>Serpent; I will put enmity between thy Seed</hi> and of the <hi>Woman;</hi> and <hi>this Seed of the Woman, the one Seed,</hi> Chriſt ſhall <hi>break the Head</hi> of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> Gen. 3. unto perfect <hi>Victory;</hi> and <hi>Thou ſhall bruiſe His Heel;</hi> (of which is preſently to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken;) There muſt be therefore a Seed of the <hi>Second Adam;</hi> Servants of God in every Generation, who ſhall <hi>Fight, Finiſh their courſe,</hi> Hold <hi>the Faith</hi> of the <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Woman,</hi> the <hi>Second Adam,</hi> the <hi>Lord from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> the <hi>Quickning Spirit, the Saviour to the uttermoſt, who Lives for ever to make Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,</hi> and ſo ſuſtains all the Servants of God, <hi>coming to God by Him;</hi> He Bears them up in their State of <hi>Preiſthood,</hi> as the <hi>Preiſt for ever; Conſtituted after the Power of an Endleſs Life,</hi> conſecrated by the <hi>word of the Oath for evermore; the High Preiſt and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of our Profeſſion,</hi> the <hi>Captain of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> This ſupports the whole State of the Servants of God in all the Service here recounted here by the Apoſtle; <hi>Fighting, Running, Finiſhing their courſe</hi> in order to the <hi>Receiving the Crown:</hi> And thus the Line of the ſucceſſion of the Servants of God hath
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151275:22"/>been continued from <hi>Adam</hi> through all Ages. From <hi>Adam</hi> by the <hi>Patriarks,</hi> to <hi>Moſes, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah,</hi> the <hi>Judges, Kings, Prophets, Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel,</hi> and <hi>Ezra,</hi> ſo to the Great <hi>Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in his Temple,</hi> Malach. 3.1. Then the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and ſucceſſive <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> Revel. 11.3. in the Time of the <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> who being the Laſt courſe of the Servants of God; There is an expreſs mention of that Firſt Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of things; <hi>the Serpent</hi> early appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as a <hi>Dragon</hi> in the <hi>Slaying Abel;</hi> and the <hi>Seed of the Woman,</hi> He endeavoured to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> by <hi>making War with them,</hi> by the <hi>Beaſt. Who kills them,</hi> and <hi>they Lye Dead in the ſtreet of the Great City;</hi> Till the <hi>Spirit of Life from God enter into them;</hi> And then the courſe of things goes on to the <hi>Binding</hi> the <hi>Dragon, Sathan, the Old Serpent, Chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Sealing</hi> up in the <hi>Abyſs,</hi> in his own <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Chains</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort Looſing to ſhew his ever remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Diabolick</hi> Spirit, we have with all his <hi>Dead</hi> His Final <hi>Caſting</hi> into the <hi>Lake,</hi> which is the <hi>Second Death:</hi> And thus we have the Firſt Point cleared, How comes there to be ſuch a Line and Succeſſion of the <hi>Preiſts,</hi> or <hi>Servants</hi> of the <hi>Moſt High God</hi> in ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate a Humane Nature? And how Long? Even till they come into the Glorious State of being <hi>Preiſts</hi> of God and Chriſt, and <hi>Reigning with Him a Thouſand Years; ſeeing His Face, as His Servants ſerving Him</hi> with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151275:22"/>His <hi>Name on their Foreheads,</hi> and at Laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd up with the <hi>Kingdom to God All in All;</hi> which is the State of pure, and perfect Eternity, <hi>Eternal Life</hi> in its Higheſt Orb.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Point.</hi> 2. I come therefore now to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Point; How comes it to paſs, there is ſuch a ſtrict Limitation of the Servants of God: Firſt under ſuch an Honourable Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as <hi>Fighting</hi> the Good <hi>Fight,</hi> even unto Victory; their <hi>Finiſhing</hi> their <hi>eourſe,</hi> even unto <hi>obtaining</hi> the <hi>Prize;</hi> and their <hi>Keeping the Faith,</hi> without betraying, <hi>Baſely</hi> ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, or having <hi>made Shipwrack</hi> of it; and ſo preſenting it before the <hi>Righteous Judge,</hi> and receiving the <hi>Crown at that Day;</hi> All theſe are Honourable, and yet Limitations; Their <hi>Fight, Courſe, Keeping the Faith</hi> are not Leng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd out to that very Day; Now of this there are very Great Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Great Lord of Time hath drawn the whole time with ſuch exactneſs of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Holineſs; That every thing is in its own Place, Seaſon, and Time; and as it fills that up, and nothing is wanting, ſo it cannot exceed, nor reach beyond it; And thus <hi>Every thing is Beautiful in its ſeaſon;</hi> Thus from the very Beginning; <hi>Abel</hi> the Firſt Martyr <hi>Finiſhed</hi> his <hi>Courſe,</hi> though ſhort; <hi>Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> theirs; In the midſt of whom appeared <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec, made like to the Son of God, without Beginning of Days,</hi> or End of Life, Abridgeth a <hi>Preiſt continually;</hi> He was not a Type of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151275:23"/>
               <hi>Son of God</hi> in ſome particular excellency, but <hi>He was made like to the Son of God througout;</hi> And thus is the Line of every Saints ſervice drawn out, nothing can crowd into it; and this Line can by no Violence be cut ſhorter, nor can any Zeal for Service draw it out longer; The only Elect Servant is He, whoſe Service hath no Limitation; but, as was ſaid, <hi>The Son Conſecrated by the Word of the Oath for evermore; and conſtituted after the Power of an Endleſs Life: Melchiſedec</hi> therefore, who was made like Him, was under no Limitation of Service in the Hiſtory we have of Him: <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cohs Patriarchal</hi> Line reach'd even to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and there ceaſed; <hi>Moſes Faithful in All his Houſe</hi> Run that whole, and very Great Line of Service in the <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> but was ſo Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, He muſt by no means enter into <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> but muſt Dye in the Borders; And <hi>Joſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> muſt enter upon his Courſe; and having ſettled the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and after the <hi>Lord had given them reſt round about; He Finiſhed his courſe.</hi> Then came on the <hi>Days</hi> of the <hi>Judges,</hi> and their courſe with <hi>Samuel</hi> reached (with the Intervention of <hi>Saul</hi>) unto <hi>David,</hi> who <hi>ſerved his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration according to the Will of God;</hi> And ſo the Line came down to <hi>John Baptiſt Fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling</hi> his <hi>courſe,</hi> as a <hi>Forerunner;</hi> and ſo to our <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> who <hi>walked,</hi> as He ſaid in his courſe here on Earth, (though as the <hi>Son, an Eternal Preiſt) this Day,</hi> and to <hi>Morrow;</hi> and the <hi>Third Day</hi> ſhould be <hi>perfected.</hi> Then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151275:23"/>the courſe of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> under a moſt Definitive Line, as hath been ſaid: This therefore gives great ſatisfaction in the Term of Life; Calls for Great ſelf-Reſignation, and to have our Eye Fixed on the Great End of Life, the Line of Faith and Service.</p>
            <p>It is true, There is a Line allowed to Evil Men in their Wickedneſs, and in their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of their Luſts, and Pleaſures of this World; and they cannot exceed it; But this is not of the preſent conſideration; But it is moſt neceſſary here to remember; That the Loweſt and Meaneſt, even the Infant Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God have their Line and Service, and the Juſt Times of it Fixed by God; even as their Reward; becauſe it is wholly the Reward of Free Grace, It is in the eſſence of the Reward equal, as hath been argued.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Time of the Servants of God is therefore Defined, and Limited; That it may be ſeen, God hath no need of this, or that Servant, or Generation of Servants; but that He hath ſucceſſive Servants, or Generations of Servants; and He is ſo Far off being in want of them; That He can allow them no longer Time, how Eminent, how Excellent ſoever, then He hath appointed, and reſolved with Himſelf; and of Free Grace, as their Honour and Priviledge, choſen them unto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Servants of God are <hi>many;</hi> That they may reach through, and unto the Time of his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> And each muſt have His
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151275:24"/>Time; and each muſt therefore, of thoſe, who go before, give way to thoſe, who are to follow after; and ſo every one is Limited to his own Time; For though it may be thought; They might be together; The Wiſe God having appointed Times more Dark, and more Glorious; How many of his Servants are proportion'd to each, He ſees, and knows, and ſo Limits accordingly: There was one <hi>Noah,</hi> and no more in the Old World; One <hi>Elijah</hi> only in view, in that ſo Fowl <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of the <hi>Ten Tribes;</hi> And when the Light is cleareſt and moſt High, It muſt not be clear Light till his Kingdom. The General Aſſembly cannot be before, ſo each Time hath ſuch, and ſuch <hi>Numbers</hi> of <hi>Stars,</hi> which He <hi>telleth the Number</hi> of, and <hi>calleth them All by their Names,</hi> and knoweth, what Luſtre of Rays and Beams each and together ſhall caſt; There is a Counterpoizing conſideration of Wicked Men in the World, and the <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Fire</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> they ſpread; But that is not within the preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is a Gracious Pleaſure of God; There ſhould ſuch Numbers of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants be all along from Age to AGe with <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt their Lord,</hi> Philip. 1. <hi>Diſſolved</hi> from Body, and with Him in Spirit; <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Body,</hi> and <hi>preſent with the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in their <hi>Houſe not made</hi> with <hi>Hands, Eternal in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens;</hi> And that <hi>our God may come</hi> and <hi>All
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151275:24"/>His Saints with Him,</hi> Zech. 14. <hi>He cometh with Ten Thouſand of his Saints,</hi> as the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Heaven on white Horſes, Bodys of the Reſurrection waſhed in the Blood of Jeſus, in fine Linnen, clean, and white,</hi> Rev. 19.14. To ſhew, This hath been all along from the former Times of the World; There is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in Heaven Styled, <hi>Abrahams Boſome; A Jeruſalem above, the Mother of us All,</hi> that ſhall <hi>come down from Heaven,</hi> Gal. 4. With all its <hi>Children,</hi> Rev. 21. There is the State of the <hi>Spirits of Juſt Men,</hi> Heb. 12. Who ſhall be <hi>made perfect in Bodys, made like to his Glorious Body,</hi> Phil. 3. <hi>ult.</hi> There muſt be therefore a Limitation of their Time of Service here below; That they may be taken within the <hi>Veil</hi> and made acquainted with the Glory, that is to be <hi>Revealed;</hi> And the Apoſtle Intimates; Theſe <hi>Dead in Chriſt</hi> ſhall have ſome precedency; For the <hi>Dead in Chriſt,</hi> ſhall not be <hi>prevented</hi> by the <hi>Living Remaining,</hi> as we Tranſlate; but ſhall not be ſo much, as overtaken according to the true force of the Original; we ſhall not <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> or <hi>come equal</hi> with thoſe aſleep, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> c. 4. v. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Nullo Modo Aſſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur;</hi> Now in all ſuch Particularities, God is pleas'd to be at Liberty in dealing with His own Servants; The eſſential Glory, the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> the <hi>Crown of Life,</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> being alike, ſure to all: And ſo I have open'd the ſecond Point pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd; The Limitation of the Time of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151275:25"/>Servants of God, <hi>continuing</hi> in His <hi>Service</hi> here on Earth; I come to the <hi>Point</hi> 3d.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Limitation of their Time is made known to them in the manner of a ſevere, and angry Proceſs, in the way of, what we Call, a <hi>Prohibition,</hi> the proper ſenſe of what we Tranſlate, <hi>not ſaffered,</hi> Heb. 7.23. And this is a Point worthy to be enquired into for the removing the fears of Death, and for the Conſolation of Saints in Death.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt then be Acknowledg'd, that the outward Face, and appearance of Death, hears the Reſemblance of a <hi>Judgment,</hi> and of that Denunciation, <hi>In the Day thou Eateſt, thou ſhalt Dye; Duſt thou Art,</hi> and to <hi>Duſt thou ſhalt return.</hi> It comes, as a <hi>King of Terrors, Fleſh and Blood</hi> is ready to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted at it; Life is naturally Dear, even to the Servants of God; who deſire not to be <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloathed;</hi> They deſire to continue in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God here; but when they are raiſed by Higher Conſiderations of being <hi>preſent with the Lord, Clothed upon with their Houſe from Heaven,</hi> they even deſire to be <hi>Diſſolved.</hi> And it cannot be denyed; That God doth in the Dying of his Servants bear a Regard to that Juſtice, and Truth of His Word; That when <hi>Sin came in, Death came in and paſſed upon All, becauſe All have ſinned,</hi> Rom. 5.12. When the Servants of God therefore are warm and zealous, and lively in His Service, Often there comes a <hi>Prohibition;</hi> Thou mayeſt no longer continue in my Service
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151275:25"/>here; like the command to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to anoint <hi>Eleazar</hi> and to ſtrip <hi>Aaron</hi> of his Prieſtly Garments, who was preſently to Dye; A <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>carry Iſrael</hi> over <hi>Jordan,</hi> but to come up to <hi>Mount Nebo</hi> and to Dye; <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. God plainly ſent to <hi>Hezekiah, to ſet His Houſe in Order</hi> and to <hi>Dye;</hi> againſt which <hi>Prohibition</hi> that it might be under, as it were an Arreſt of Judgment, He ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly Prayed.</p>
            <p>It is therefore to be duly conſidered; That for the Diſplay of the Judgment, and Indignation of God againſt ſin, and becauſe of the preſent State of the Saints under a Remaining <hi>Body of Sin,</hi> and ſo of <hi>Death;</hi> and in the preſent State of this World, full of Sin and Evil, and of ſo many of the Children of <hi>Adam, Children of Death,</hi> even of the <hi>Second Death;</hi> In the Wiſdom and Holineſs of God, It was by the Counſel of the Father, and the Son, that <hi>Death</hi> ſhould continue, and have the Face of a Judgment, and of a <hi>Legal Prohibition</hi> to continue in the Service of God any longer on Earth; Till the Kingdom of Chriſt, the Kingdom of Redemption ſhould bring in a State of the <hi>Living</hi> Saints, then <hi>Remaining</hi> being <hi>chang'd,</hi> and not to <hi>Dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Becauſe the Children</hi> were <hi>Partakers</hi> of <hi>Fleſh and Blood,</hi> He <hi>took part of the ſame,</hi> that <hi>through Death,</hi> He <hi>might ſubdue Him, that had the Power of Death;</hi> that is, the <hi>Devil;</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:151275:26"/>and <hi>Deliver</hi> them, who <hi>all their Life were ſubject to Bondage by reaſon of the Fear of Death;</hi> and now therefore Death came upon Him with the Violence, and Terror of a <hi>Judgment</hi> from which He was taken and from <hi>Priſon,</hi> Eſa. 53.8. By the Mighty Power of his Reſurrection; It becomes all His to ſubmit then to the Face of a Judgment in Dying, that they may be conform'd to their <hi>Captain</hi> and from the Firſt Born, Heb. 2.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It may be Objected againſt this neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Dying, How were thoſe two <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> exempted from that ſentence of the Righteous, and Holy Law that is ſtretched out ſo upon all; ſeeing ſin had extended it ſelf on them, as well, as on others?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Death of Jeſus Chriſt, ſtood as a <hi>Full Ranſom,</hi> and Price of Redemption from the very firſt promiſe, ſo that it is not indeed a Point of Juſtice, or of the Truth of God; That Believers in Jeſus Chriſt are ſerved (as I may ſo ſpeak) with a <hi>Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> by <hi>Death;</hi> but a Wiſe, and Holy Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Government with Relation to the Servants of God in the preſent World; where therefore, in that wiſe Government God thinks ſit; there might be ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from the General Statute of Dying, or <hi>Prohibition</hi> by <hi>Death,</hi> as of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Flijah;</hi> and many more Examples of ſuch, Exemptions, there might have been, if He had ſeen Good, having received ſuch full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to his Law, and to his Juſtice;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151275:26"/>and He hath it in reſerve an Univerſal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption at the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>Redemption;</hi> when the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>We ſhall not all dye,</hi> but <hi>we ſhall all be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged;</hi> and he prefaces before it: <hi>Behold I ſhew you a myſtery;</hi> And I am much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded and even aſſured; Theſe two were Types of the <hi>Living, Remaining caught up</hi> to <hi>meet</hi> the <hi>Lord in the Air,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. <hi>When he delivers up the Kingdom</hi> to <hi>God, even the Father,</hi> and hath <hi>put down all Rule Authority,</hi> and the <hi>laſt Enemy Death is ſubdued</hi> and <hi>caſt into the Lake;</hi> then ſhall the <hi>Living Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining</hi> Saints be Tranſpoſed, or caught up, as <hi>Enoch;</hi> and even conveyed to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as <hi>Elijah</hi> in the <hi>Charriot</hi> of that <hi>Fire,</hi> that devours the Adverſaries, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9, 14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Judiciary part of Death is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely removed; <hi>For the Sting of Death is Sin,</hi> and the <hi>ſtrength of Sin is the Law, but thanks be to God</hi> who hath <hi>given us the Victory</hi> through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.12. So that Death is to Saints, <hi>a ſleeping in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, a Reſting from Labours, an entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Reſt, a becoming preſent with the Lord; A being with Chriſt, a being in Paradiſe, a being clothed upon with our Houſe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> And to ſhew, It was not a Deadly ſtroke; Before the Pronunciation of that Univerſal <hi>Prohibition</hi> of continuing here;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151275:27"/>
               <hi>Duſt thou Art, and to Duſt thou ſhalt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn;</hi> Death was more gently expreſs'd, and with aſſurance of <hi>Victory; The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Seed ſhall break the Serpents Head,</hi> but the <hi>Serpent</hi> ſhall only <hi>Bruiſe the Heel of the Womans Seed, This Body of Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> I will now by way of Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Review, cloſe the whole; How fit this Context of the Apoſtle is to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with Relation to the Death of one, or more of the Servants of God, appears by the Apoſtles Preface to it; I am even now as it were ready to be as in Conformity to my Great Lord, Offered, and Sacrificed, as a <hi>Martyr,</hi> and the <hi>Time</hi> of my <hi>Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is at <hi>Hand;</hi> and ſo He goes on, <hi>I have Fought,</hi> &amp;c. As if He Preached his own <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> while Living, and a Great one it is; but it hath its Principal ſenſe in Chriſt; and in God; as appears in the following Part of the Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 17. wherein we have this Great acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, that in his <hi>Fighting the Good Fight, and Finiſhing his Courſe, the Lord ſtood with Him, ſtrengthened Him; that by Him the Preaching might be Fully known, and the Gentiles hear; and the Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered Him, out of the Mouth of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Lord would deliver Him from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Evil Work, and preſerve Him unto His Heavenly Kingdom, and to Him he aſcribes the Glory of All for Ever;</hi> And He In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151275:27"/>all Saints; Even all, who <hi>Love the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in this High <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium,</hi> or Speech of Praiſe; elſe I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, I have no Opinion of the Large <hi>Encomiums,</hi> or Praiſings uſed in Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermons, obſerving the Grand Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar of them; Gods Gracious Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Joſhua 1. <hi>Moſes my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant is Dead,</hi> and no more; and yet that Fixed ſo Laſting a Character of Honour upon Him; that He is remembred by it to the Laſt, Rev. 15. <hi>They Sang the Song of Moſes the Servant of God, and of the Lamb:</hi> But this of the Apoſtle Joyned with that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.23. Gives me ſuch a Hiſtory of the Life and Death of Saints; That I cannot, but Recommend it to all the Servants of Chriſt, as the moſt excellent Rule of Life, and as the Ground of the moſt Conſolatory <hi>Hope in Death;</hi> and that the very Diſcourſe of it may be upon the Deceaſed Chriſtian Friend, a Memorial of Honour; And ſo I moſt Humbly Recommend it to the Relations of all the Friends of the ſo many lately Removed Servants of God, and of this Particular one, on the occaſion of whoſe Death it is Publiſhed; through Him, who though the <hi>Eternal Liver,</hi> as the <hi>Son of God,</hi> without <hi>Beginning,</hi> or <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Days;</hi> yet in our Nature <hi>Became Dead</hi> for our ſakes; but behold He is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151275:28"/>
               <hi>Alive for Evermore; Even ſo</hi> have all his Servants Reaſon to ſay; <hi>Even ſo Amen.</hi> And He hath the <hi>Keys of Hell;</hi> and <hi>Death;</hi> Let Him <hi>Lay His Hand</hi> on the <hi>Servants of God</hi> in this Diſcourſe, and Bleſs it to Them; and on his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of all States and Conditions; ſaying unto them, <hi>Fear not. And to Him be Glory for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce the Finiſhng and Printing this forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Diſcourſe, it hath pleaſed the ſupreme Lord of his Servants State in this Work, to lay his <hi>Prohibition</hi> on the <hi>Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sir. Edward Harley,</hi> to continue on longer in his Service here; to whoſe Memory, although I am every way obliged; yet in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Him I ſhall only ſay, <hi>Sir Edward Harley the Servant of God is Dead.</hi> Oh That many ſuch may be ſound unto his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in his Service.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>The leſſer Faults of the Preſs, let the Reader pleaſe to Correct, and Note theſe, Preface <hi>Page</hi> 2. line 18. r. Mr. T. <hi>Gouge. pag.</hi> 9. l. 3. at the bottom, f. <hi>it</hi> r. <hi>if,</hi> p. 11. l. 5. Bot. blot <hi>un,</hi> p. 21. l. 16. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 23. l. 7. blot <hi>are,</hi> p. 33. Bot. 2d. f. <hi>abridgeth,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth, p. 37. Bot. l. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 41. l. 9. before <hi>He,</hi> r. <hi>when,</hi> l. 12. f. <hi>when,</hi> r. <hi>then,</hi> l. 18. after <hi>them,</hi> r. <hi>viz. Saints.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
